Hi.
مرحباً.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
[Jennifer Brea is sound-sensitive.
[تعاني جينيفر من حساسية من الأصوات.
The live audience was asked to applaud ASL-style, in silence.]
طلب من الحضور التصفيق دون صوت.]
So, five years ago, this was me.
ها أنا ذا منذ خمس سنوات.
I was a PhD student at Harvard,
درست الدكتوراه في جامعة هارفرد،
and I loved to travel.
ولطالما أحببت السفر.
I had just gotten engaged to marry the love of my life.
وقد تقدم الشخص الذي أحبه للزواج بي.
I was 28, and like so many of us when we are in good health,
كنت في الثامنة والعشرين وكنت كباقي الناس حين نكون بصحة جيدة،
I felt like I was invincible.
أعتبر أن الصحة من المسلمات.
Then one day I had a fever of 104.7 degrees.
وذات يوم ارتفعت حرارتي إلى 104.7 درجة.
I probably should have gone to the doctor,
كان علي أن أراجع الطبيب
but I'd never really been sick in my life,
إلا أنني قلما مرضت في حياتي،
and I knew that usually, if you have a virus,
وكنت أعلم أنه غالبا، أن أصبت بفيرس ما،
you stay home and you make some chicken soup,
تحتاج للمكوث في المنزل واحتساء شوربة الدجاج،
and in a few days, everything will be fine.
ومن ثم يتم الشفاء خلال أيام.
But this time it wasn't fine.
لكن الأمر كان مختلفاً هذه المرة.
After the fever broke,
بعد ارتفاع الحرارة،
for three weeks I was so dizzy, I couldn't leave my house.
شعرت بدوار في رأسي لثلاثة أسابيع ولم أستطع مغادرة المنزل.
I would walk straight into door frames.
كنت أتسنَّد على حواف الأبواب
I had to hug the walls just to make it to the bathroom.
وأعانق الجدران كي أصل إلى الحمام.
That spring I got infection after infection,
توالت علي الإصابات طوال ذلك الربيع،
and every time I went to the doctor,
وفي كل مرة أزور طبيباً،
he said there was absolutely nothing wrong.
يقول أن كل شيء على ما يرام.
He had his laboratory tests,
خضعت لفحوص مخبرية،
which always came back normal.
والنتيجة دائماً طبيعية.
All I had were my symptoms,
كنت أعاني أعراضاً وحسب،
which I could describe,
ولم أستطع وصفها،
but no one else can see.
ولم يلحظها أحد.
I know it sounds silly,
قد يبدو الأمر سخيفاً
but you have to find a way to explain things like this to yourself,
إلا أن شعوراً بالإلحاح اعتراني لتفسير ما يحدث،
and so I thought maybe I was just aging.
وخطر لي أن يكون السبب عائد للتقدم في السن.
Maybe this is what it's like to be on the other side of 25.
ربما أنها أعراض طبيعية عند تخطي سن الخامسة والعشرين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Then the neurological symptoms started.
ثم ظهرت الأعراض العصبية.
Sometimes I would find that I couldn't draw the right side of a circle.
تارة يصعب علي رسم نصف دائرة.
Other times I wouldn't be able to speak or move at all.
وتارة أخرى أعجز عن الكلام أو الحركة.
I saw every kind of specialist:
راجعت مختلف أنواع الأخصائيين:
infectious disease doctors, dermatologists, endocrinologists,
أطباء الأمراض المعدية، أطباء جلدية، أطباء الغدد الصماء
cardiologists.
أطباء قلبية.
I even saw a psychiatrist.
كما زرت طبيباً نفسياً.
My psychiatrist said, "It's clear you're really sick,
قال لي "يبدو أنك متوعكة،
but not with anything psychiatric.
لكنك سليمة من الناحية النفسية.
I hope they can find out what's wrong with you."
آمل أن يتم تشخص الخلل لديك."
The next day, my neurologist diagnosed me with conversion disorder.
في اليوم التالي، تم تشخص حالتي بـ"اضطراب التحويل".
He told me that everything --
أخبرني أن الأعراض --
the fevers, the sore throats, the sinus infection,
الحرارة، التهاب الحلق، التهاب الجيوب الأنفية
all of the gastrointestinal, neurological and cardiac symptoms --
جميع الأعراض الهضمية والعصبية والقلبية --
were being caused by some distant emotional trauma
كانت ناجمة عن صدمة عاطفية ما
that I could not remember.
تعذر علي تذكرها.
The symptoms were real, he said,
قال أن الأعراض حقيقية
but they had no biological cause.
لكن ليس ثمة سبب بيولوجي لها.
I was training to be a social scientist.
كنت أعد لأكون باحثة اجتماعية.
I had studied statistics, probability theory,
درست الإحصاءات ونظرية الاحتمالات،
mathematical modeling, experimental design.
والنمذجة الرياضية والتصميم التجريبي.
I felt like I couldn't just reject my neurologist's diagnosis.
لم أقوَ على رفض تشخيص طبيب الأعصاب.
It didn't feel true,
لم أشعر أن ما قاله صحيحاً،
but I knew from my training that the truth is often counterintuitive,
لكنني تعلمت أثناء التدريب أن الحقيقة تأتي غالباً مخالفة للحدس،
so easily obscured by what we want to believe.
يسهل حجب الحقيقة وراء ما نريد أن نصدقه.
So I had to consider the possibility that he was right.
كان علي الأخذ بعين الاعتبار احتمال صواب ما يقوله.
That day, I ran a small experiment.
في ذلك اليوم، أجريت تجربة صغيرة.
I walked back the two miles from my neurologist's office to my house,
عدت من عيادة طبيب الأعصاب إلى منزلي سيراً على الأقدام،
my legs wrapped in this strange, almost electric kind of pain.
شعرت بوخز في قدمي أشبه بلسعة كهربائية.
I meditated on that pain,
رحت أركز تفكيري على الألم،
contemplating how my mind could have possibly generated all this.
وكنت أتساءل كيف لعقلي أن يولد كل هذا الكم من الألم.
As soon as I walked through the door,
وعندما دخلت من خلال الباب،
I collapsed.
أُصبت بالانهيار.
My brain and my spinal cord were burning.
شعرت بنار تسري في عقلي ونخاعي الشوكي.
My neck was so stiff I couldn't touch my chin to my chest,
وكانت عنقي متيبسة لدرجة أنني لم أستطع ملامسة صدري بذقني،
and the slightest sound --
أبسط الأصوات --
the rustling of the sheets,
حركة المارة في الشارع،
my husband walking barefoot in the next room --
وقع أقدام زوجي في الغرفة المجاورة --
could cause excruciating pain.
كلها تتسبب في ألم مبرح.
I would spend most of the next two years in bed.
مكثت معظم السنتين التاليتين في السرير.
How could my doctor have gotten it so wrong?
كيف لطبيبي أن يخطئ التشخيص؟
I thought I had a rare disease,
ظننت أنني أعاني من مرض نادر،
something doctors had never seen.
مرض لم يسبق للأطباء أن شهدوه من قبل.
And then I went online
ثم هرعت للإنترنت
and found thousands of people all over the world
ووجدت آلاف الأشخاص حول العالم
living with the same symptoms,
يعانون نفس الأعراض،
similarly isolated,
معزولون مثلي،
similarly disbelieved.
مثلي لا أحد يصدقهم.
Some could still work,
بعضهم واصل عمله،
but had to spend their evenings and weekends in bed,
لكنهم يقضون أمسياتهم وعطلاتهم الأسبوعية في السرير،
just so they could show up the next Monday.
كي يستجمعوا قواهم لبدء أسبوع جديد.
On the other end of the spectrum,
أما البعض الآخر،
some were so sick
فكانوا بحالة صحية سيئة للغاية
they had to live in complete darkness,
مما دفعهم للانزواء في أماكن مظلمة تماماً،
unable to tolerate the sound of a human voice
عاجزين عن احتمال أي صوت بشري
or the touch of a loved one.
أو أي لمسة ممن حولهم.
I was diagnosed with myalgic encephalomyelitis.
تم تشخيص إصابتي بمرض التهاب الدماغ والنخاع المؤلم للعضل.
You've probably heard it called "chronic fatigue syndrome."
ربما يُعرف باسم "متلازمة الوهن المزمن."
For decades, that's a name
وقد شاع الاعتقاد أن هذه التسمية
that's meant that this
تعني أن هذه الأعراض
has been the dominant image
تمثل الانطباع الشائع
of a disease that can be as serious as this.
عن مرض قد يكون بهذه الخطورة.
The key symptom we all share
العَرَض الرئيسي المشترك
is that whenever we exert ourselves -- physically, mentally --
أن أدنى جهد جسدي أو عقلي
we pay and we pay hard.
يجلعنا نكابد معاناة كبرى.
If my husband goes for a run, he might be sore for a couple of days.
عندما يمارس زوجي الركض يصاب أحياناً بالتهاب بسيط في الحلق.
If I try to walk half a block, I might be bedridden for a week.
لكن مشية قصيرة بالنسبة لي ترديني في السرير لأسبوع كامل.
It is a perfect custom prison.
أشبه بسجن كامل المواصفات.
I know ballet dancers who can't dance,
أعرف راقصي باليه فقدوا القدرة على الرقص،
accountants who can't add,
ومحاسبين يعجزون عن القيام بمهامهم،
medical students who never became doctors.
وطلاب طب لم يصبحوا أطباء.
It doesn't matter what you once were;
مهما كان النشاط الذي تمارسه،
you can't do it anymore.
لن تتمكن من ممارسته بعد.
It's been four years,
بعد أربع سنوات،
and I've still never been as well as I was
لم أستطع العودة إلى حالتي الطبيعية
the minute before I walked home from my neurologist's office.
قبل لحظة عودتي إلى البيت من عيادة طبيب الأعصاب.
It's estimated that about 15 to 30 million people around the world
حوالي 15 - 30 مليون شخص حول العالم
have this disease.
مصابون بهذا المرض.
In the US, where I'm from, it's about one million people.
في الولايات المتحدة، حيث ولدت، يقدر عدد المصابين بمليون شخص.
That makes it roughly twice as common as multiple sclerosis.
أي ضعف عدد المصابين بمرض التصلب المتعدد.
Patients can live for decades with the physical function
يعيش المرضى لعقود مع أعراض بدنية
of someone with congestive heart failure.
تشبه تلك الناجمة عن فشل القلب الاحتقاني.
Twenty-five percent of us are homebound or bedridden,
25 بالمئة من المرضى يلزمون منازلهم أو ـسرتهم،
and 75 to 85 percent of us can't even work part-time.
و75 إلى 85 بالمئة لا يستطيعون العمل حتى بدوام جزئي.
Yet doctors do not treat us
ومع ذلك، فإن الأطباء لا يعالجوننا
and science does not study us.
والعلم لا يدرس حالتنا.
How could a disease this common and this devastating
كيف لمرض بهذا الانتشاروالأثر الهدّام
have been forgotten by medicine?
أن يتم تجاهله من قبل الطب؟
When my doctor diagnosed me with conversion disorder,
عندما شخص الطبيب حالتي باضطراب التحويل،
he was invoking a lineage of ideas about women's bodies
كان يستحضر أفكاراً عن أجساد نساء
that are over 2,500 years old.
تزيد أعمارهن عن 2,500 سنة.
The Roman physician Galen thought
اعتقد الطبيب الروماني (غالين)
that hysteria was caused by sexual deprivation
أن الهستيريا ناجمة عن الحرمان الجنسي
in particularly passionate women.
وخاصة عند النساء الشبقات.
The Greeks thought the uterus would literally dry up
واعتقد اليونانيون أن الرحم قد يجف تماماً
and wander around the body in search of moisture,
ثم يتجول في أنحاء الجسم بحثاً عن الترطيب.
pressing on internal organs --
مما يضغط على الأعضاء الداخلية --
yes --
أجل --
causing symptoms from extreme emotions
وينتج عن ذلك أعراض تتراوح من التقلبات العاطفية
to dizziness and paralysis.
إلى الدوار والشلل.
The cure was marriage and motherhood.
وكان العلاج يتمثل بالزواج والإنجاب.
These ideas went largely unchanged for several millennia until the 1880s,
بقيت هذه الأفكار سائدة بشدةلآلاف السنين حتى ثمانينات القرن التاسع عشر،
when neurologists tried to modernize the theory of hysteria.
حين حاول أطباء الأعصاب بتحديث نظرية الهستيريا.
Sigmund Freud developed a theory
طور (سيغموند فرويد) نظرية
that the unconscious mind could produce physical symptoms
تفيد بأن العقل اللاواعي قد ينتج أعراضاً فيزيائية
when dealing with memories or emotions
عند التعامل مع ذكريات أو عواطف
too painful for the conscious mind to handle.
شديدة الألم لدرجة تتجاوز قدرة العقل الواعي.
It converted these emotions into physical symptoms.
فيقوم بتحويل هذه العواطف إلى أعراض بدنية.
This meant that men could now get hysteria,
أي أن الرجال معرضون للإصابة بالهستيريا
but of course women were still the most susceptible.
لكن النساء هنَّ الأكثر تأثراً بهذا المرض.
When I began investigating the history of my own disease,
عندما بدأت البحث في تاريخ المرض الذي أعانيه،
I was amazed to find how deep these ideas still run.
أكتشفت أن هذه الأفكار لا تزال سائدة بشدة.
In 1934,
في عام 1934،
198 doctors, nurses and staff at the Los Angeles County General Hospital
أصيب 198 شخص بين أطباء وممرضين في مشفى لوس آنجلس العام
became seriously ill.
بوعكة صحية خطرة.
They had muscle weakness, stiffness in the neck and back, fevers --
عانوا من ضعف وتصلب عضلي في العنق والظهر وارتفاع حرارة --
all of the same symptoms I had when I first got diagnosed.
نفس الأعراض التي عانيت منها عند تشخيص المرض لدي.
Doctors thought it was a new form of polio.
ظنَّ الطبيب أنه نوع جديد من شلل الأطفال.
Since then, there have been more than 70 outbreaks documented
منذ ذلك الوقت، تم توثيق أكثر من 70 حالة تفشي
around the world,
حول العالم
of a strikingly similar post-infectious disease.
لمرض مشابه جداً يظهر بعد العدوى.
All of these outbreaks have tended to disproportionately affect women,
كانت جل هذه الحالات من النساء دون سبب واضح.
and in time, when doctors failed to find the one cause of the disease,
وعندما فشل الأطباء باكتشاف السبب الوحيد للمرض
they thought that these outbreaks were mass hysteria.
ظنّوا أن هذه الحالات ليست إلا هستيريا شديدة.
Why has this idea had such staying power?
من أين تستمد هذه الفكرة الراسخة قوتها؟
I do think it has to do with sexism,
لا أعتقد أن المسألة تتعلق بالجنس
but I also think that fundamentally, doctors want to help.
لكنني على يقين أن الأطباء يحاولون المساعدة.
They want to know the answer,
يريدون معرفة الإجابة،
and this category allows doctors to treat what would otherwise be untreatable,
يتيح هذا التوجه للأطباء معالجة الأمراض المستعصية،
to explain illnesses that have no explanation.
وتقديم شرح عن الأمراض المبهمة.
The problem is that this can cause real harm.
المشكلة تتمثل بأن هذا التوجه قد يلحق الأذى الحقيقي.
In the 1950s, a psychiatrist named Eliot Slater
في خمسينات القرن الماضي، قام طبيب نفسي يدعى (إليون سليتر)
studied a cohort of 85 patients who had been diagnosed with hysteria.
بإجراء دراسة على 85 مريضاً تم تشخيصهم بمرض الهستيريا.
Nine years later, 12 of them were dead and 30 had become disabled.
بعد تسع سنوات، 12 منهم لقى مصرعه وأصيب 30 مريضاً بالشلل.
Many had undiagnosed conditions like multiple sclerosis,
لم يتم تشخصي الكثير من أعراضهم كالتصلب المتعدد،
epilepsy, brain tumors.
والصرع وأورام الدماغ.
In 1980, hysteria was officially renamed "conversion disorder."
في عام 1980، سمِّيت الهستيريا رسمياً بـ"اضطراب التحويل".
When my neurologist gave me that diagnosis in 2012,
عندما قام طبيبي بذلك التشخيص في عام 2012،
he was echoing Freud's words verbatim,
كان يتمتم كلمات (فرويد) بشكل حرفي
and even today,
وحتى اليوم،
women are 2 to 10 times more likely to receive that diagnosis.
فإن النساء أكثر عرضة لتلقي تشخيص كهذا.
The problem with the theory of hysteria or psychogenic illness
تكمن المشكلة في نظرية الهستيريا أو الاضطراب نفسي المنشأ
is that it can never be proven.
بعدم إمكانية إثبات صحتها.
It is by definition the absence of evidence,
ويعود ذلك لغياب الدليل.
and in the case of ME,
وفي حالتي،
psychological explanations have held back biological research.
فإن التوضيحات السيكولوجية عرقلت البحث البيولوجي.
All around the world, ME is one of the least funded diseases.
التهاب الدماغ ينال الحصة الأقل من التمويل بين باقي الأمراض.
In the US, we spend each year roughly 2,500 dollars per AIDS patient,
في الولايات المتحدة، ننفق سنوياً حوالي 2,500 دولار لكل مريض إيدز،
250 dollars per MS patient
و250 دولار لمريض التصلب المتعدد
and just 5 dollars per year per ME patient.
و5 دولارات فقط لمريض التهاب الدماغ.
This was not just lightning.
هذه ليست مجرد توعية.
I was not just unlucky.
لا يتعلق الأمر بالحظ.
The ignorance surrounding my disease has been a choice,
الجهل الذي يحيط بالمرض الذي أعانيه هو خيار،
a choice made by the institutions that were supposed to protect us.
اتخذته المؤسسات التي يفترض أن تحمينا.
We don't know why ME sometimes runs in families,
لا أعلم لماذا ينتشر التهاب الدماغ ضمن العائلات،
why you can get it after almost any infection,
وما الذي يجعل الإصابة به ممكنة بعد انتقال أي عدوى،
from enteroviruses to Epstein-Barr virus to Q fever,
من الفيروسات المعوية إلى فيرس إبشتاين-بار وحمى Q،
or why it affects women at two to three times the rate of men.
أو لماذا تصاب النساء أكثر من الرجال بضعفين أو ثلاثة أضعاف؟
This issue is much bigger than just my disease.
المسألة أكبر من مجرد مرض.
When I first got sick,
عندما أصبت بالمرض،
old friends were reaching out to me.
كان بعض الأصدقاء القدماء يتواصلون معي.
I soon found myself a part of a cohort of women in their late 20s
لأجد نفسي ضمن تجمع من النساء في أواخر العشرينات من العمر
whose bodies were falling apart.
بأجساد أصابها الوهن.
What was striking was just how much trouble we were having
المؤلم في الأمر كم المعاناة التي كنا نكابدها
being taken seriously.
لنُؤخذ على محمل الجد.
I learned of one woman with scleroderma,
عرفت امرأة تعاني تصلب الجلد،
an autoimmune connective tissue disease,
اختلال في النسيج الضام للمناعة الذاتية،
who was told for years that it was all in her head.
وقد قيل لها لسنوات أن هذا المرض مجرد وهم.
Between the time of onset and diagnosis,
ومنذ إصابتها إلى أن تم التشخيص،
her esophagus was so thoroughly damaged,
كان قد لحق الأذى بالمريء،
she will never be able to eat again.
ولم تعد تستطع تناول الأكل.
Another woman with ovarian cancer,
ثمة امرأة أخرى تعاني من سرطان المبيض
who for years was told that it was just early menopause.
وقيل لها لسنوات أن تلك أعراض مبكرة لسن اليأس.
A friend from college,
إحدى صديقاتي من الجامعة،
whose brain tumor was misdiagnosed for years as anxiety.
تم تشخيص ورمها الدماغي على أنه مجرد قلق وحسب.
Here's why this worries me:
إليكم أسباب قلقي حيال الأمر:
since the 1950s, rates of many autoimmune diseases
منذ عام 1950، عدد المصابين بأمراض المناعة الذاتية
have doubled to tripled.
تضاعف ليصل إلى ثلاثة أضعاف.
Forty-five percent of patients who are eventually diagnosed
45 بالمئة من المرضى الذين يتم تشخيصهم في النهاية
with a recognized autoimmune disease
باضطراب في المناعة الذاتية
are initially told they're hypochondriacs.
قد أُخبروا في البداية أنها مجرد وساوس.
Like the hysteria of old, this has everything to do with gender
كمرض الهستيريا مثلاً، الأمر مرتبط بالجنس
and with whose stories we believe.
وهذا مبني على قصص نصدقها.
Seventy-five percent of autoimmune disease patients are women,
75 بالمئة من أمراض المناعة الذاتية هم من النساء،
and in some diseases, it's as high as 90 percent.
وفي بعض الأمراض تصل النسبة إلى 90 بالمئة.
Even though these diseases disproportionately affect women,
ومع أن هذه الأمراض تصيب النساء دون سبب واضح،
they are not women's diseases.
فهي لا تقتصر على النساء.
ME affects children and ME affects millions of men.
فمرض الالتهاب الدماغي يصيب الأطفال وملايين الرجال.
And as one patient told me,
وكما قال لي أحد المرضى،
we get it coming and going --
أن المرض ينتشر ويختفي --
if you're a woman, you're told you're exaggerating your symptoms,
إذا كنت امرأة، فيخبرونك أنك تبالغين بالأعراض
but if you're a guy, you're told to be strong, to buck up.
لكن إذا كنت رجلاً فيخبرونك أن تتحلى بالشجاعة والقوة.
And men may even have a more difficult time getting diagnosed.
وربما يعاني الرجال أكثر في أثناء مرحلة التشخيص.
My brain is not what it used to be.
لم يعد عقلي كما كان سابقاً.
Here's the good part:
إليكم الجانب الجيد:
despite everything, I still have hope.
على الرغم من كل ذلك، لا زال لدي أمل.
So many diseases were once thought of as psychological
فالكثير من الأمراض اعتبرت في البداية أنها سيكولوجية
until science uncovered their biological mechanisms.
إلى أن جاء العلم ليكشف عن آلياتها البيولوجية.
Patients with epilepsy could be forcibly institutionalized
وقد تم حجر المصابين بالصرع بالإجبار
until the EEG was able to measure abnormal electrical activity in the brain.
إلى أن ساعد الرسم الكهربائي للدماغ بقياس النشاط الكهربائي المعتل.
Multiple sclerosis could be misdiagnosed as hysterical paralysis
تم تشخيص التصلب المتعدد بالشلل الهستيري
until the CAT scan and the MRI discovered brain lesions.
إلى أن ساعدت الأشعة المقطعية والرنين المغناطيسي باكتشاف الخلل الدماغي.
And recently, we used to think
ويشيع مؤخراً الاعتقاد
that stomach ulcers were just caused by stress,
بأن قرحة المعدة سببها التوتر وحسب،
until we discovered that H. pylori was the culprit.
لنكتشف فيما بعد أنها تعود لجرثومة في المعدة.
ME has never benefited from the kind of science
ولم ينل الالتهاب الدماغي اهتماماً كافياً من العلم
that other diseases have had,
كما الأمراض الأخرى،
but that's starting to change.
لكننا بدأنا نتلمس التغيير.
In Germany, scientists are starting to find evidence of autoimmunity,
ففي ألمانيا، يحقق العلماء اكتشافات في مجال المناعة الذاتية
and in Japan, of brain inflammation.
والتهاب الدماغ ، في اليابان.
In the US, scientists at Stanford are finding abnormalities
في الولايات المتحدة، علماء في (ستانفورد) يعثرون على اختلالات
in energy metabolism
في استقلاب الطاقة
that are 16 standard deviations away from normal.
والتي تمثل 16 انحرافاً معيارياً عن الحالة الطبيعية.
And in Norway, researchers are running a phase-3 clinical trial
وفي اليونان، يجري الباحثون تجربة سريرية من ثلاث مراحل
on a cancer drug that in some patients causes complete remission.
على عقار لمعالجة السرطان أحدث شفاء كلياً عند بعض المرضى.
What also gives me hope
أستمد الأمل أيضاً
is the resilience of patients.
من قدرة المرضى على المقاومة.
Online we came together,
نجتمع سوية عبر الإنترنت،
and we shared our stories.
ونتشارك قصصنا الذاتية.
We devoured what research there was.
نمحِّص أي بحث متوفر.
We experimented on ourselves.
ونجري التجارب على أنفسنا.
We became our own scientists and our own doctors
وقد أصبحنا علماء وأطباء أنفسنا
because we had to be.
فقد اضطررنا لذلك.
And slowly I added five percent here, five percent there,
وقد أضفت 5 بالمئة هنا 5 بالمئة هناك،
until eventually, on a good day,
إلى أن أتى يوم جميل،
I was able to leave my home.
استطعت فيه مغادرة المنزل.
I still had to make ridiculous choices:
ولا زالت تلك الأسئلة السخيفة تراودني:
Will I sit in the garden for 15 minutes, or will I wash my hair today?
هل أمكث في الحديقة لربع ساعة، أو هل سأحمم شعري اليوم؟
But it gave me hope that I could be treated.
لكنها تمدني بالأمل لعل الشفاء قادم.
I had a sick body; that was all.
لدي جسد واهن، هذا كل ما في الأمر.
And with the right kind of help, maybe one day I could get better.
ومع توفر الرعاية الصحيحة قد تأخذ صحتي بالتحسن.
I came together with patients around the world,
اجتمعت بمرضى من جميع أنحاء العالم،
and we started to fight.
وبدأنا نقاوم المرض.
We have filled the void with something wonderful,
ملأنا الفراغ بنشاطات رائعة
but it is not enough.
لكن ذلك لا يكفي.
I still don't know if I will ever be able to run again,
لا أعلم إذا كنت سأتمكن يوماً من ممارسة الركض مجدداً،
or walk at any distance,
أو السير على الأقدام،
or do any of those kinetic things that I now only get to do in my dreams.
أو القيام بالنشاطات الحركية التي تراودني في أحلامي.
But I am so grateful for how far I have come.
إلا أنني أشعر بالامتنان لما حققته حتى الآن.
Progress is slow,
التقدم بطيء،
and it is up
يعلو تارة،
and it is down,
وينخفض تارة أخرى،
but I am getting a little better each day.
لكنني أتحسَّن يوماً بعد يوم.
I remember what it was like when I was stuck in that bedroom,
أذكر تماماً ذلك الشعور عندما كنت حبيسة الفراش،
when it had been months since I had seen the sun.
حيث لم أكن أرى الشمس لأشهر عديدة.
I thought that I would die there.
ظننت أنها النهاية.
But here I am today,
لكن ها أنا اليوم
with you,
معكم،
and that is a miracle.
وهذا بحد ذاته معجزة.
I don't know what would have happened had I not been one of the lucky ones,
لا أعلم ماذا كنت سأفعل لو لم أكن من المحظوظين،
had I gotten sick before the internet,
لولا وجود الانترنت،
had I not found my community.
لولا الأشخاص الذين وجدتهم.
I probably would have already taken my own life,
ربما كنت سأضع حداً لحياتي،
as so many others have done.
كما فعل الكثير غيري.
How many lives could we have saved, decades ago,
كم من روح كنا لننقذ منذ عشرات السنين،
if we had asked the right questions?
لو أننا طرحنا الأسئلة الصحيحة؟
How many lives could we save today
كم من روح كنا لننقذ اليوم.
if we decide to make a real start?
لو اتخذنا القرار بانطلاقة حقيقية؟
Even once the true cause of my disease is discovered,
حتى لو اكتشفنا السبب الحقيقي لهذا المرض،
if we don't change our institutions and our culture,
إذا لم نغير مؤسساتنا وثقافتنا،
we will do this again to another disease.
فسنتعاطى بنفس العقلية مع مرض آخر.
Living with this illness has taught me
علمني التعايش مع هذا المرض
that science and medicine are profoundly human endeavors.
أن العلم والطب يمثلان مسعى إنسانياً عميقاً.
Doctors, scientists and policy makers
الأطباء والعلماء وصناع السياسات
are not immune to the same biases
معرضون أيضاً لنفس الأمراض
that affect all of us.
مثلنا تماماً.
We need to think in more nuanced ways about women's health.
نحتاج لفهم دقيق لصحة المرأة.
Our immune systems are just as much a battleground for equality
أجهزتنا المناعية تحتاج لنفس القدر من الرعاية
as the rest of our bodies.
تماماً كباقي أعضاء جسدنا.
We need to listen to patients' stories,
نحتاج للإصغاء لقصص المرضى،
and we need to be willing to say, "I don't know."
يلزمنا شجاعة لنقول: " أنا لا أعرف."
"I don't know" is a beautiful thing.
فاللامعرفة أمر إيجابي.
"I don't know" is where discovery starts.
فمن اللامعرفة تبدأ الاكتشافات.
And if we can do that,
إذا أمكننا ذلك،
if we can approach the great vastness of all that we do not know,
إذا تمكنا من تلمس مواطن اللامعرفة الواسعة لدينا،
and then, rather than fear uncertainty,
عندئذٍ، لن نخاف من شكوكنا،
maybe we can greet it with a sense of wonder.
بل سنرحب بها مع شعور بالفضول.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.